[birds chirping]
[man]
Hey, I wanna ask you something.
I want you to be honest,
all right?
Okay.
You got any regrets?
[acoustic guitar music]
♪ Oh, coal river ♪
♪ Won't you wash
my bones away ♪
♪ I'm slaving for the company ♪
♪ And I can't get any pay ♪
♪ Well, mining coal ♪
♪ Ain't a way to make a life ♪
♪ And I can't feed the hunger ♪
♪ Of three kids and a wife ♪
♪ Now the hollers are empty ♪
♪ And the company left town ♪
♪ And there ain't
no more mountain ♪
10-1, 10-1.
You dead or alive down there,
buddy?
If you are dead,
can I keep the truck? Over.
[walkie-talkie crackles]
I'm in the main tunnel.
Ain't no one been in here
in a hundred years
And no you don't get
to keep no damn truck.
Over.
-What's it like down there?
-[debris falling]
-It's spooky. Over.
-[walkie-talkie crackles]
Keep your eyes on the prize,
brother. Nut up and shut up!
- Over.
-[walkie-talkie crackles]
Easy for you to say.
[ominous music]
[chain rattles]
[faint rustling]
[water dripping]
-[walkie-talkie crackles]
-Some strange shit down here.
But there's coal, alright.
Over.
Hallelujah,
how much we talking?
Over.
Sealed shut.
Old gas seal, maybe.
[ominous music]
Jesse, you copy?
There's something...
Something is inside there.
[ominous music builds]
[door creaks]
[boom and rumbling]
[over walkie-talkie] Jesse,
get the hell out of there,
Jesse!
[ominous music builds]
[explosion]
[child imitates engine revving]
[woman] You've seen with your
own eyes what they're doing
next door at Rock Creek.
Dynamiting the mountain.
-Spitting lead into the air.
-[rumbling]
Arsenic into the river.
They ain't here to hire us.
They're here for the land.
So we get new homes.
Ain't nothing special about
this holler over any other.
We got elderly.
We got young.
Not everybody can up
and move on.
[Bo] When we got money.
We'll figure it out.
[distant explosion]
I got offered 50 large.
Now when am I gonna see
another $50,000
in this lifetime?
If you sell,
if any of us sells,
they'll use court precedent
to sue to get the rest
of the plots,
just like they done at Hobet.
Now maybe you get 50 grand
in your pocket,
but the rest of us,
we'll be lucky if we get five.
You gonna sell out your Ma?
Your cousin?
-Your uncle on the plot over?
-KC.
Your folks've been here
longer than any of us.
What do you say?
I saw coal dust
on the patio today.
Coming down out of the sky
like it was snow.
The same black dust that
got into my daddy's lungs.
Chase, he turns ten tomorrow.
He was out there playing in it.
It ain't right.
[somber music]
We'll put it to a vote.
[ominous music]
[on TV] Just two hours ago,
Allied Air Forces
began its attack on military
targets in Iraq and Kuwait.
These attacks continue
as I speak.
Hey, Meemaw.
[on TV] Ground forces
are not engaged.
This conflict started
August 7th.
[mailbox opens]
[on TV] ...a small and helpless
neighbor.
Kuwait, a member
of the Arab League...
-[KC] Any good news?
-[on TV] ...was crushed.
[explosion, ground shaking]
[utensils clatter]
[on TV] We will also destroy
his chemical weapons
facilities.
[wind howls]
[distant explosion]
[birds chirping]
[lighter ignites]
[lighter snaps shut]
Thanks.
What if we did get out?
You heard Doc.
We'd be selling out everyone
we know.
Josie can't travel,
not with her lungs.
But this here land might
be worth a lot more than
they're letting on.
[Jesse] I went down that old
wildcat mine down the holler.
There's coal down there, KC,
maybe a lot.
You went down there
and you didn't tell me?
Look, you said you're worried
about Chase.
I am too. I just...
I want to know our options.
I'm sorry, alright?
I should have told you.
This here's your family land.
You gotta be the one to decide.
This is the only home
I've ever known.
To let them win after
all they've done?
[insect buzzing]
We gonna figure it out.
Don't you go down
that mine again.
I won't.
Promise me.
Yeah, I do.
Okay.
[uplifting music]
You're annoying.
[laughs]
[uplifting music continues]
[coughing]
You all right, bud?
[coughs]
Alright.
It's your birthday tomorrow
You're gonna be ten years old.
Imagine that.
How about you and me,
we go down the New River gorge
tomorrow and catch some trout?
Okay.
[coughs]
[music intensifies]
[coughs heavily]
[coughing continues]
[explosion]
[machines clatter]
[Jesse] We got some back taxes
we can't can't pay.
Bank is threatening
foreclosure.
[rattling]
Look, son, I'mma level with you.
The price on condemned land,
if we take it through
eminent domain,
it ain't much.
But if there is coal
underneath there,
and we can do a direct sale,
well then we can talk turkey!
[laughs]
KC would never agree to that.
[Lawson] That's a damn shame.
[clears throat]
Hey, do you hunt?
-Buck season's coming up.
-Yeah.
[Lawson]
Well, let me show you something.
[clears throat]
6.3 tons on that big boy!
Can you believe that?
[Lawson]
See, that right there is me,
and that man next to me,
you might recognize
from being on TV on account
that he sits on the US Senate.
Have you ever been on a safari,
Jesse?
[scoffs]
-No.
No, I figure you ain't never
even left the county. Have you?
That right?
Hell, you can't even pay
your mortgage.
Fuck this.
[camera thuds]
-What's that?
-That is an offer.
[Lawson]
Look, son, we're gonna
take the land either way.
Just a matter of when.
And how long before
that bank moves in?
What? A few weeks?
And they gonna take it anyway.
And leave you with nothing?
Just help us get what we need,
Jesse.
And you'll be compensated.
And the real question is,
how can you go home
and look that pretty little wife
of yours in the eye
if you don't?
[ground shakes]
♪ Dark is the coal dust
and deepest of night ♪
♪ The only grave
you will know ♪
♪ For the cold night
is coming ♪
♪ It'll call you inside ♪
♪ And fill you with trouble ♪
What are you doing?
♪ Dark is the coal dust ♪
♪ That burns in your lungs ♪
♪ The only breath
you will know ♪
♪ For the old dark is coming ♪
♪ It'll turn you to stone ♪
♪ And fill you with trouble ♪
[explosion]
[debris falling]
♪ Come home ♪
♪ Come home to your love ♪
[paper burns]
♪ I'll feel the fire that burns
in your eyes ♪
♪ And leave all your ♪
♪ Trouble ♪
Time for bed.
But I wanna go fishing.
What did I tell you?
[sighs] If ifs and buts
were candy and nuts,
every day would be Christmas.
That's right.
Go.
[TV playing]
-[object rattles]
-I don't wanna hear it.
You've been waiting to say
"I told you so" since the day
we were married.
So what? He dealt a little dope
when he was a kid.
Did a little time.
Who didn't around here?
[dishes rattle]
-I'm gonna go look for him.
-[object rattles]
That ain't kind
and that ain't true.
-[bell jingles]
-We'll talk when you can
be nice.
[object rattles heavily]
[ominous music]
[engine shuts off]
[loud music playing]
[knock on door]
[knocks heavily]
[loud music continues]
Is Jesse in there?
-Why don't you fuck off?
-[door slams]
Jesus, KC!
I told you, he ain't here.
How old is she?
How am I supposed to know?
Maybe when we go ask
Sheriff Henley, then?
Hey, that ain't funny.
Do I look like a fucking clown?
-He's with Bo Brown. Okay?
-Where?
Jesus, KC. I don't know.
Probably drunk.
He'd be home sooner if
you quit hounding him.
Hey, look, I didn't sell
nothing, okay? I swear.
Don't you start.
Shit, Jesse. What did you do?
[car engine turns on]
[heavy object thuds]
[water drips]
[door creaks]
[Jesse] You got the carbon
monoxide detector?
About that...
[Bo] Woah now, settle down.
What the hell you got in there?
I couldn't get my hands
on a CMD.
So I brung old Dusky here.
[cat meows]
That's a cat, Bo.
Yeah. Ain't you never heard
of a cat in a coal mine?
It's a canary, dumbass.
It's a bird.
Yeah, I caught me a bird too.
But Dusky ate it.
Anyway, I figure it's
the same in principle.
-[cat growls]
-Out your damn gourd.
Well come on.
Well, maybe I should stay here.
[cat meows]
Give me the cat then.
Why?
Because what if there's gas?
I don't want no harm
to come to her.
It's Dusky.
-Bo, give me the cat.
-No.
Give me the cat, Bo.
Give me the cat.
You're scaring her.
[cat meows]
-[water drips]
-[cat meows]
-It's okay, Dusky.
It's all right.
[rope tightens]
[ominous music]
Tug twice if you get in trouble.
This place is huge.
[Bo] You see any coal?
[ominous music continues]
It's all coal.
[camera shutter clicks]
[ominous music continues]
[music intensifies]
[debris clatters]
Bo?
[ominous music]
Is that you?
Well lookie here.
-Finders keepers.
-[cat meows]
Oh!
Dusky.
[ground rumbles]
[rope tightens]
Oh, shit.
[rope snaps]
[music intensifies]
[ominous music]
[footsteps approaching]
[Bo] Oh, shit!
[screaming]
[KC] He's been missing
since yesterday.
Well, how long do I
gotta wait to report it?
Look, it ain't like him.
Yeah.
Yeah, okay.
I understand.
Shit.
[vehicles approaching]
What the hell?
[ominous music]
[trucks pass by]
[miners talking]
Hey!
Well, howdy, ma'am.
This here's a company mine.
For right now, I'm gonna have
to ask you to keep off
the property.
You're Dorsey Cayton.
You used to drive
with my daddy Jeb.
You must be KC.
Yeah.
So you know for a fact that
this ain't your land,
and you
got no right to be here.
All I know is what's
right here in black and white.
You can take it up with the home
office, but I can't do nothin'
for ya.
And I can't let you pass.
-Is Jesse in there?
-[Dorsey] Jesse?
What you want with that junkie?
Wait...
Don't tell me you went
and married him.
[laughs]
Hey, I'm kiddin'.
What's the matter?
You can't take a fuckin' joke?
Get out of my way.
[body thuds]
[grunts in pain]
You know, they used to
talk about you on the pit.
Jeb's little girl had
something of a reputation.
A real fuckin' skank!
Fuck you.
What I heard, you like to
squeal like a stuck fuckin' pig!
[Dorsey imitates snorting]
[hooting and hollering]
[truck approaching]
[truck engine stops]
Oh, hi. Ma'am, can you just
have a seat in the corner?
Ma'am, excuse me.
Your goddamn thugs
are on my land,
and my goddamn husband
is missin'.
[receptionist]
I am so sorry, sir.
KC, we've been tryin' to
get hold of you.
-Why don't you sit down?
-Where's Jesse?
Sit?
For my sake.
Now listen, I don't know how
to tell you this,
but it seems like you ain't
got word, so here it is.
I got a call a few hours ago
from the boys runnin' GPR.
Your Jesse was in that mine
during a partial collapse.
-What?
-Now I want you to know
I am doing
everything in my power
to try to save that boy.
Did you send him down there?
-Point of fact, he volunteered.
-You're lying.
And even if you ain't,
I want you off my land.
I'll find him myself.
Look, let me put this
to you simple.
[paper rustles]
It ain't your land no more, KC.
I made Jesse an offer,
and he took it.
[paper rustles sharply]
[paper crumples]
That's all right, we got copies.
It's a fuckin' forgery.
-Prove it.
-I will, I'll sue you.
Mm-hmm. Yeah, and it'll be
your word against his.
And without him there
in court to testify,
well, good luck.
[distant explosion]
[bangs table]
[car door slams]
Fuck.
[grunts]
[heavy breathing]
[sobbing]
[TV playing]
[on TV]
You know, it's hard to believe.
It's hard to believe
when we haven't kept
this issue from every time.
When we have men
and women standing
preaching and teaching,
it is hard to believe that men
are at low sight on heaven
and that's about a good boy.
[coughing]
Told you so.
[TV continues playing]
[phone ringing]
Manhattan is expecting a report.
You know what's at stake
for our investors.
Now look, things work
different down here.
You gotta work the people.
Our bosses know this and that is
why they put me in charge of it.
Results, Lawson.
[crickets chirping]
[paper rustles]
Jesse?
[crickets chirping]
Hey, who's there?
[eerie music]
[snarling]
[panting]
-[Jesse] KC help me
-[KC] No!
Help me
Help me, KC! Help me!
-Help me KC, please!
-[screaming]
[coughing]
[gasping]
[rain pattering]
[lightning crashing]
Chase!
Hey, hey, little bean.
Little bean, come on.
You're all right.
You're all right. Hey, Come on.
Hold still, it's gonna sting,
okay?
Okay.
What's this?
[ominous music]
Where did you get this?
Chase.
The coal man gave it to me.
-[distant thunder rumbling]
-Okay.
Let's get you back to bed, okay?
Okay.
[birds chirping]
[squelching]
[wind blowing]
[birds chirping]
Hey, open up.
[door creaks]
Cricket?
[shaky breathing]
[gasping]
[sniffs]
Jesse's in trouble.
We gotta warn him.
It's too late.
He and Bo got trapped down
a Mine Shaft.
-It can't be.
-Well, it is.
It ain't KC, Bo was here.
Last night he came in,
coughing, hacking up a lung.
He was begging me for a hit,
scared as shit.
I think he got me sick.
Where the hell is he now?
I called the Black Lung
Clinic and they,
they came and took him.
The one up in Kingwood?
-I gotta go.
-KC, you been dreaming?
I've been having this one
over and over.
It's, it's dark.
It's-- it's like my feet
sliding into the ground.
Like, like,
like it's pulling me in.
In this dream,
something's hunting me.
Something from down in the
mountain hollers or some--
It ain't human.
Get some rest.
[ominous music]
[coughing]
[breathing]
[receptionist]
Breathing center.
[distant coughs]
[machine beeping]
Oh, shit, Bo.
[gasping]
Okay, okay, okay, okay.
-[gasping and coughing]
-Here, put it back.
-No. [gasping]
-It's okay.
You gotta get me out of here,
KC.
[wheezing] They know I got out.
They don't want me to talk.
-Raleigh coal?
-Please, KC.
What happened, Bo?
Is Jesse alive?
I don't know.
That blackness in the earth,
brushed up against
some greater dark.
What?
Don't let them open up
the mountain, KC.
I closed it back up, but
you've seen what it done to me
in just one second.
Don't let it out.
[coughing]
-Hey!
-[heavy coughing]
[gasping]
-Get me out of here.
-Okay! Okay!
I got Meemaw's spare breather
in the truck.
I'll fetch it.
[heavy coughing]
Mrs. Scarbro.
What brings you
to Kingwood today?
And you are?
My name is Eli.
Visiting a relative.
[Eli] Relative.
Would that happen to be,
Bo Brown?
[laughs]
You're blocking my truck.
Mm.
Shit.
-[car door shuts]
-[light flickers]
[distant coughs]
[loud tone]
Bo?
-[grunts]
-Hey!
-[beep]
-[KC] Oh, no. Bo!
Bo! Oh, shit.
[sustained beep]
Hey, will somebody
get the fuck in here?
[heavy breathing]
Hey!
Hey, hey, hey, hey!
Stop!
Stop, stop, stop!
No, no, no!
Hey!
Oh, shit.
Meemaw? Chase?
Come on, Jesse.
Where'd you stash it?
Fuck.
[cocks gun]
[TV playing]
Hey, Ma.
-[sighs in relief]
-[TV continues playing]
[breathing heavily]
Hey, little bean.
Go, get in.
Seatbelt!
[car engine turns on]
Where are we going?
Taking you to Doc and Tipper's
to stay a while.
Why?
Keep you safe is why.
Because of the coal man?
[sniffles]
Well ain't you a little miracle.
Go on.
[car engine turns on]
[heavy breathing]
[sizzling]
[grunting in pain]
[high pitched static]
[rain pattering]
[sighing heavily]
[Jesse]
What you doing, KC?
Coming to get you, that's what.
[Jesse] What you think
you're gonna find down there
in all that dark?
Don't matter.
You got others that need you
more than my junky ass.
You ain't real,
so I don't gotta listen to you.
It ain't gonna let you, KC.
What ain't?
That what's down the mountain.
It's hungry.
It wants out.
It's coming.
[eerie music]
[door creaks]
[growling]
[intense music builds]
[persistent honking]
[tires screeching]
[panting]
-[TV playing]
-[heavy breathing]
[object rattling]
[coughs]
Give me a cigarette.
No, Meemaw, you know you can't.
You just shoot somebody?
Maybe.
You get to shoot a sumbitch.
I get to have smoke.
Bo's dead.
He was sick with something.
He said something real bad
got in him down there.
And Cricket had it too.
What's down that mountain?
Cigarette.
[coughs]
[lighter ignites]
[coughing]
What's down there...
[eerie music]
...it ain't the coal.
It's what drives men to dig it.
We gotta keep it caged.
Jesse's alive down there,
I can feel it.
Don't you go after him, girl.
There ain't no curse here.
It's just plain greed
and sickness.
I'm gonna go get him out.
And then we're all gonna
get out.
I know that this is home.
But it ain't worth this.
You've got a responsibility
to this land.
I got a responsibility
to my family.
[twig snaps]
[heavy breathing]
-[shouting]
-[heavy knocking]
What the hell, Cricket?
What are you doing?
-It's after me.
-What is?
Huntin me down
like a goddamn whistle pig.
You calm down,
there ain't nothing there.
[gasping] You look.
[panting]
You're pie-eyed is all.
See?
[heavy breathing]
Is it Raleigh after you?
The Yankee in the coat?
It ain't no Yankee.
It ain't a man at all.
You're talking crazy.
Ain't you got a gun in here?
It's in the truck.
[eerie music]
[heavy breathing]
[roof creaking]
[footsteps approaching]
[dishes rattling]
Just some critter.
[sobbing]
[door creaking]
Cricket?
Meemaw.
[loud thump]
[heavy breathing]
[door creaks]
[sniffling]
[breathing heavily]
Come on out, Cricket.
Not with that booger I ain't.
There ain't no booger.
Grow a fucking sack, man.
[heavy breathing]
Come on.
I'mma get you cleaned up.
Get a little coffee in you,
my God.
What?
Run.
[eerie music]
[growling]
[KC gasps]
[roars]
[splatters]
[hand thuds]
-[screaming]
-[splatters]
[panting]
-[door rattles]
-[panting]
-[screaming]
-[door bursts open]
[panting]
[screaming]
[shattering]
[panting]
[roars]
-[heavy impact]
-[body falls]
Git.
-[heavy impact]
-[tank falls]
[KC] Hey!
[glass breaks]
[roars]
[tires screeching]
[growling]
[heavy impact]
[heavy breathing]
[panting]
-[cocking gun]
-[panting]
[growls]
[gun firing]
[panting]
Oh, Jesus, meemaw.
No, no, no, no, no, no,
Come on.
You're okay, you're okay,
[hisses]
I'll get the spare.
You're okay, you're okay,
you're okay.
-Come on.
-[rattling]
[Josie grunts in pain]
Come on.
You piece of shit come on.
No, no, no, no, no, no.
[gasping]
That's good!
That's good, Meemaw.
That's right.
Just breathe.
[sizzling]
[cocking gun]
[gun firing]
[phone ling ringing]
-[Doc] Hey, hello.
-Doc, it's KC.
[Doc] This here's Doc and
Tipper's message machine.
-Go on and leave us one then.
-[beeps]
Doc, it's KC, you give me a
call back as soon as you can.
[phone hangs up]
[panting]
[coughs]
[heavy breathing]
[screaming]
[phone ringing]
Doc, Doc, is that you?
Is Chase all right?
[muffled heavy breathing]
Doc?
[over phone] Mrs. Scarbro,
do you know who I am?
You killed Bo...
[over phone]
Bo Brown carried the flame.
He did not have
the will to become it.
Go to hell.
[Chase] Ma?
Chase?
You son of a bitch,
what do you want?
[over phone] You know.
Where?
[over phone]
You know that, too.
[sustained beep]
[car approaching]
[explosion]
[glass breaks]
♪ And then ♪
-♪ I'm born to die ♪
-[shotgun loads]
♪ To lay days high enough ♪
♪ And my ♪
[lightning strikes]
♪ Life happens here in my ♪
♪ Into a world ♪
♪ Unknown ♪
[thunder rumbles]
Let him go.
[wheezing]
The gun...
[heavy breathing]
Come.
You let go my Mama!
Stop it, stop it.
Chase, no, you be good.
You already took our land,
you took our home.
Just let us go.
Don't you want to see
your Jesse again?
Where is he?
We are...
family.
And family must be united.
[grunts heavily]
What the fuck?
[screaming]
Run, Chase!
[gun firing]
-[bullet impact]
-[body thuds]
[birds chirping]
You got any regrets?
Yeah, I got my share.
But I guess you ain't
one of them.
[panting]
[lighter ignites]
[distant rumbling]
[panting]
Chase?
[distant rumbling]
Chase!
[heavy breathing
over walkie-talkie]
Jesse?
Hold on, okay?
[walkie-talkie beeps]
[sparkler ignites]
[grunts]
Stay back.
I said stay fucking back.
[roars]
[sparkler falls]
[scuffling]
[roars]
[screaming]
[heavy impact]
[grunts]
[jackhammer rattles]
[screaming]
[jackhammer drills]
[roars]
[screaming]
[gasping]
[squelching]
[grunting]
Chase.
I found Daddy.
[jackhammer starts]
KC.
[gasping]
I'm sorry.
For what I've done.
We should have just gone.
There ain't no leavin it.
Oh, come on.
You gotta try.
[panting]
Time to go, little man.
Jesse...
[grunting]
[roars]
Go.
[panting]
[grunts]
Go!
[heavy grunting]
To hell with you!
[screaming]
[roars]
[grunting]
Go.
[coughing]
[gasping]
[heavy breathing]
[TV Announcer]
There was a huge explosion.
There's been
a lot of dynamite involved.
[somber guitar music]
[Lawson, on TV] Rest assured,
we will continue
to fight for clean coal jobs
for Americans
and we will be moving forward
with the trout mountain dig
at the soonest viable
opportunity.
Jesse?
Fight ain't over yet.
They'll just keep coming
again and again.
You're a good girl,
KC Scarbro.
Make your family proud.
[sobbing]
[sobbing continues]
♪ Well you ain't got no life
anymore ♪
♪ You stay in a dark
coal mine ♪
♪ Working away every day ♪
♪ With your wife and kids
on your mind ♪
[coughing]
♪ You wake up in the
morning and grab
your hard hat ♪
♪ Pray that you make it
back home ♪
♪ Your body is aching and you
just can't take it ♪
♪ Mining that dark black hole ♪
♪ Dark black coal
take my soul ♪
♪ Owe it to you anyways ♪
♪ Just don't let my children
become the victims ♪
♪ Of the mountain's evil ways ♪
♪ And you miss being younger ♪
♪ A boy with a hunger ♪
♪ To get far away
from this town ♪
♪ You never knew how ♪
♪ Why or when ♪
♪ Just knew that you'd make it
somehow ♪
♪ Now 20 years older
shoulder to shoulder ♪
♪ The boys who were
just like you ♪
♪ Spending their lives
underground ♪
♪ Proving their collars
are blue ♪
♪ Dark black coal
take my soul ♪
♪ Owe it to you anyways ♪
♪ Just don't let my children
become the victims ♪
♪ Of the mountain's evil ways ♪
♪ Dark black coal
take my soul ♪
♪ Owe it to you anyways ♪
♪ Just don't let my children
become the victims ♪
♪ Of the mountain's evil ways ♪
♪ Don't go down ♪
♪ To dig the company's grave ♪
♪ Don't go down
that dark hole ♪
[soft music]
♪ Don't go down ♪
♪ Where no love
nor light can live ♪
♪ Don't seek your doom
beneath the ground ♪
♪ Don't go down
that dark hole ♪
[soft music]
♪ Don't go down ♪
♪ And fill your lungs
with coal ♪
♪ Wherever you rock
and brace of earth ♪
♪ Could cleave you
from your soul ♪
♪ Don't take
the foreman's dollar ♪
♪ He's just paid you
to die ♪
♪ Don't sign
the company's papers ♪
♪ Don't go down
that dark hole ♪